<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sumehta.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sumehta.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-01T05:25:16+00:00</updated><id>https://sumehta.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Sneha Mehta&apos;s homepage </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Grokking Raspberry Pi 5</title><link href="https://sumehta.github.io/blog/2024/raspi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grokking Raspberry Pi 5"/><published>2024-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sumehta.github.io/blog/2024/raspi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sumehta.github.io/blog/2024/raspi/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="setting-up-raspberry-pi-5-a-beginners-guide">Setting Up Raspberry Pi 5: A Beginner’s Guide</h1> <p>As a first-time Raspberry Pi (RasPi) user, diving into the world of DIY computing can be both exciting and daunting. Recently, I embarked on this journey myself with the purchase of a Raspberry Pi 5 (8GB) Canakit for $176 from Canakit’s website, a trusted Raspberry Pi reseller. In this blog post, I’ll share my experiences and learnings in setting up the Raspberry Pi 5 for my specific needs, hoping to provide a helpful guide for fellow beginners.</p> <h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started</h2> <p>Before diving into the assembly and setup process, it’s essential to understand your objectives with the Raspberry Pi. My goal was to create a personal web server to host my applications and potentially make them accessible over the internet.</p> <h2 id="unboxing-and-assembly">Unboxing and Assembly</h2> <p>Upon receiving the Raspberry Pi 5 Canakit with its aluminum case, I turned to online resources to guide me through the unboxing and assembly process. While there are numerous resources available, I found a particularly helpful video tutorial <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fjUkI2Hw8dY">here</a>, originally made for Raspberry Pi 4. Despite the slight discrepancy in versions, the video introduced me to the passive heat sink/cooler functionality of the aluminum case, alleviating my initial concern about the absence of a fan or additional heat sinks in the kit.</p> <h2 id="enabling-ssh-access">Enabling SSH Access</h2> <p>One of the initial challenges I encountered was enabling SSH access to Raspberry Pi 5 from my laptop. Although the Raspberry Pi 5 comes preinstalled with Raspbian 5 OS, SSH is not enabled by default. While the conventional method involves using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">raspi-config</code> to enable SSH via the bootloader menu, I found this approach ineffective. Instead, I opted to write a new Raspbian OS image onto the included MicroSD card using the Raspberry Pi Imager software. Despite the time-consuming process of approximately 30 minutes for image writing, the subsequent reboot with the custom changes ensured successful SSH access.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Setting up a Raspberry Pi 5 for the first time can be a rewarding experience with the right guidance and resources at hand. By sharing my journey and the challenges I encountered, I hope to assist fellow beginners in navigating their Raspberry Pi projects more smoothly. While there may be initial hurdles, the versatility and potential of the Raspberry Pi platform make it a worthwhile investment for DIY enthusiasts and hobbyists alike.</p> <p>Remember, the Raspberry Pi community is vast and supportive, so don’t hesitate to seek assistance and explore further possibilities for your projects. Happy tinkering!</p> <p><em>Disclaimer: Prices and availability mentioned in this post are subject to change.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Setting Up Raspberry Pi 5: A Beginner’s Guide]]></summary></entry></feed>